Finding aid to the Voices of Feminism Oral History Project oral histories SSC.MS.00535
Sophia Smith Collection
Voices of Feminism Oral History Project oral histories
1990-2014
Sophia Smith Collection
Voices of Feminism Oral History Project
SSC.MS.00535
63 oral histories
30.75 linear feet (78 boxes)
2.5 Terabytes 1,145 files (video, audio, transcripts)
Oral History Project documenting the persistence and diversity of organizing for women in the United States. Narrators include labor, peace, and anti-racism activists; artists and writers; lesbian rights advocates; grassroots anti-violence and anti-poverty organizers; and women of color reproductive justice leaders. Interviews cover childhood, personal life, and political work. Most oral histories consist of audiovisual recordings and transcripts, plus some background information.
Biographical / Historical
The Voices of Feminism Archival Development Project, funded by the Ford Foundation from 2002 to 2008, aimed to bring race, class, and sexual diversity to the holdings of the Sophia Smith Collection. The project consisted of several parts: a) searching for personal papers and organizational records of women of color, grassroots organizers, and others marginalized in traditional historical accounts, b) conducting oral histories, c) collaborating with Gloria Steinem as she works in her own papers and identifies potential donors, and d) developing plans for a video documentary series based on these new materials.
Project staff included Joyce Follet, director and oral historian; Kelly Anderson, oral historian; Sheila Flaherty-Jones, editor; Kathleen Banks Nutter, oral historian; Loretta Ross, consultant and oral historian; Revan Schendler, consultant and editor; Kate Weigand, oral historian. Interviews were also conducted by Martha Ackelsberg, Nancy MacLean, and Evelyn C. White.
Biographical information about each of the narrators is available in the finding aid, below.
Scope and Contents
The Voices of Feminism Oral History Project documents the persistence and diversity of organizing for women in the United States in the latter half of the 20th century. Narrators include labor, peace, and anti-racism activists; artists and writers; lesbian rights advocates; grassroots anti-violence and anti-poverty organizers; and women of color reproductive justice leaders. Interviews average 5-6 hours and cover childhood, personal life, and political work.
Each narrator's document box includes the recorded interview (on dvds or video tapes, plus audio CDs); the unedited and edited transcripts; correspondence between interviewer and narrator; a biographical survey; and the interviewer's guide. Some narrators' files include background materials and photographs.
Additional Formats
Digital versions of transcripts are available online through links in the container list below whenever allowed by the narrators.
Most of the video has been digitized and is available online, but restricted to access on the Smith campus only: http://media.smith.edu/departments/ssc/vof/vofvideo-list.html.
Related Material
In addition to their oral histories, the following women have donated their personal papers to the Sophia Smith Collection:
Dolores Alexander
Virginia Apuzzo
Charon Asetoyer
Joan E. Biren
Katsi Cook
Lora Jo Foo
Margaret Frantz
Marlene Fried
Ronnie Gilbert
Fran Worden Henry
Eva Kollisch
Anne MacKay
Luz Alvarez Martinez
MUSE Records
Marjory Nelson
Luz Rodriguez
Loretta J. Ross
Gloria Steinem
Linda Stout
Nkenge Touré
Carmen Vázquez
Wynona Ward
Papers are expected from: Patricia Reeve and Catherine Roma.
Related organizational records in the Sophia Smith Collection include:
Abortion Rights Fund of of Western Mass. (Fried)
Arise for Social Justice (Bewsee)
Have Justice Will Travel (Ward)
Black Women's Health Imperative (Ross, Toure)
Ms. Foundation for Women (Steinem)
Ms. magazine (Steinem)
National Congress of Neighborhood Women (Payne, Miller, Peterson)
National Network of Abortion Funds (Fried)
National Women's Health Network (Ross, Cook)
Native American Women's Health Education Resource Center (Asetoyer)
New York City Women Community Activists OHP (NCNW-Payne, Miller, Peterson)
North Fork Women for Women Fund (MacKay)
Reproductive Rights National Network (Fried and Tax)
SisterSong: Women of Color Reproductive Health Collective (Ross)
Stop It Now! (Henry)
Undivided Rights Book Project (Fried, Cook, Ross, Luz Martinez)
Women's Action Alliance (Steinem)
Conditions Governing Access
Most of the oral histories are open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of the Smnith College Special Collections.
Whenever a narrator has requested that the Sophia Smith Collection restrict access to her interview, it is noted in the finding aid below.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
As a preservation measure, researchers must use copies of the original audiovisual materials in this collection.
In-house use copies (audio CD, VHS and DVD) are available for all unrestricted interviews, and digital copies of most of the videos are available online but restricted to the Smith campus only: http://media.smith.edu/departments/ssc/vof/vofvideo-list.html. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request additional access to digital copies.
African American women--Biography--Sources; Asian American women--Biography--Sources; Birth control--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Civil rights movements--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Feminists--United States--Biography--Sources; Hispanic American women--Biography--Sources; Indian women--Biography--Sources; Jewish women--United States--Biography--Sources; Labor leaders--United States--Biography--Sources; Labor movement--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Lesbians--United States--Biography--Sources; Peace movements--United States--History--Sources; Pro-choice movement--United States--Biography--Sources; Reproductive health--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Sexual abuse victims--Biography--Sources; Women fire fighters--Biography--Sources; Women labor union members--United States--Biography--Sources; Working class women--United States--Biography--Sources; Oral history; Deming, Barbara, 1917; Feminists; Civil rights activists; Lesbian activists; Labor organizers; Reproductive rights activists; Grassroots organizers; Pacifists; Writers; Artists; Follet, Joyce; Anderson, Kelly; Nutter, Kathleen Banks; Ross, Loretta J., 1953-; Schendler, Revan; Weigand, Kate, 1965-; MacLean, Nancy; Ackelsberg, Martha A.; Hammer, Barbara; Helaine Victoria Press--History--Sources; Jackson, James E., 1914-; National Abortion Rights Action League--History; National Endowment for the Arts--History--Sources; National Organization for Women--History; National Women's Health Network (U.S.); Near, Holly; Olivia Records; Alexander, Dolores, 1931-; Apuzzo, Virginia, 1941-; Asetoyer, Charon, 1951-; Avery, Billye, 1937-; Beal, Frances, 1940-; Berek, Judith, 1943-; Berkman, Brenda, 1951-; Bewsee, Michaelann, 1947-; Biren, Joan E., 1944-; Burnham, Linda, 1948-; Casavant, Kathleen, 1951-; Chavez-Thompson, Linda, 1944-; Christian, Meg; Cook, Katsi, 1952-; Diallo, Dazon Dixon; Edgar, Joanne, 1943-; Foo, Lora; Frantz, Margaret, 1922-; Gilbert, Ronnie, 1926-; Henry, Fran, 1948-; Hollibaugh, Amber L., 1946-; Kramer, Marion, 1944; Kollisch, Eva, 1925-; Lerner, Gerda, 1920-; MacKay, Anne, 1928-; Martinez, Betita, 1925; Martinez, Luz Alvarez, 1943-; Miller, Geraldine, 1920-2005; Moraga, Cherrie, 1952-; Morales, Aurora Levins, 1954; Morales, Rosario, 1930-; Nelson, Marjory, 1928-; Nussbaum, Karen, 1950-; Payne, LaDoris, 1948; Peterson, Jan, 1941-; Pharr, Suzanne, 1939-; Powell, Achebe Betty, 1940-; Pratt, Minnie Bruce, 1946-; Reeve, Patricia, 1953-; Reynolds, Tina; Rodriguez, Luz, 1956-; Roma, Catherine, 1948-; Russell, Maura, 1954-; Saika, Peggy, 1945-; Sanchez, Graciela, 1960-; Schneir, Miriam, 1933-; Shelley, Martha, 1943-; Smith, Barbara, 1946-; Stout, Linda, 1954-; Tax, Meredith, 1942-; Thom, Mary, 1942-; Toure, Nkenge, 1951-; Vazquez, Carmen, 1949-; Voices of Feminism Oral History Project; Ward, Wynona Lund, 1951-; Winslow, Barbara, 1945-; Audiotapes; DVD video discs; CD-Roms; correspondence; Electronic mail; Computer media; Oral histories; Research; Transcripts; Videotapes; Asetoyer, Charon; Avery, Byllye, 1937-; Biren, Joan E.; Cook, Katsi; Diallo, Dázon Dixon; Foo, Lora Jo; Hayashi, Mary Chung, 1967-; Moraga, Cherríe, 1952-; Ports, Suki Terada; Ross, Loretta J.; Steinem, Gloria; Touré, Nkenge; Vázquez, Carmen M.; Kramer, Marian; Sophia Smith Collection
- Katherine Acey interviewed by Kelly Anderson, July 19, 20 and 29, 2007; Acey, Katherine; Anderson, Kelly (Box 1)
  Biographical / Historical
  Katherine Acey (b. 1950) is a highly respected activist, best known for her expertise and commitment to lesbian and women's philanthropy. Her creative and inclusive vision of funding has been instrumental in setting a standard for a more progressive, diverse and community-based definition of philanthropy.
  In 1987, after serving on Astraea's Board of Directors for four years, Katherine was hired as its Executive Director-the organization's first paid staff person. Under her stewardship, Astraea has enjoyed tremendous growth. The Foundation's Grants program has been expanded to fund local, regional and international organizations as well as cultural and media work. In 1990, Astraea established the nation's first Lesbian Writers Fund; and in 1996, Astraea created The International Fund for Sexual Minorities-the only fund of it's kind in the U.S.
  From 1982 to 1987, Katherine served as the Associate Director of the North Star Fund in New York City. She has been involved in the Women's Funding Network since its inception, serving as both board member and chair. She is also a founding member and past chair of the Funders for Lesbian and Gay Issues and has served as a board or advisory member to countless organizations including: Women in the Arts, the Center for Anti-Violence Education, New York Women Against Rape, MADRE and Women Make Movies. Katherine is past chair of the National Executive Committee of the Palestine Solidarity Committee, and a member of the Arab Women's Gathering Organizing Committee.
  Katherine has traveled extensively in the U.S. speaking on issues of philanthropy, sexual orientation, race and class. Internationally, she has participated in numerous women's and LGBTI delegations and gatherings in Africa, Asia, Central America and Europe.
  Scope and Contents
  In this oral history Katherine Acey talks about her family history, their migration from Lebanon, and the Arab American community in Utica, New York where she grew up. She reflects on her activist roots in the civil rights movement and her introduction to feminist organizing through anti-violence and reproductive rights work. The last third of the interview focuses on Katherine's work in progressive philanthropy and her twenty year tenure at the Astraea Foundation. (Transcript 62 pp.)
- Dolores Alexander interviewed by Kelly Anderson, March 20, 2004 and October 22, 2005; Alexander, Dolores; Anderson, Kelly (Box 2)
  Dolores Alexander (b.1931) was raised in a working-class Italian community in Newark, NJ, and educated in Catholic schools. She attended City College in the late 1950s. Alexander worked in journalism most of her professional life and it was in her capacity as a reporter for Newsday that she came across a press release announcing the formation of the National Organization for Women (NOW) in 1966. Alexander became NOW's first Executive Director from 1969-1970, was a co-owner of a lesbian feminist restaurant in the Village with partner Jill Ward during the 1970s, and was a founder of Women Against Pornography in the 1980s. She has been present at many significant events of the women's movement: integrating the Want Ads in the New York Times, the lesbian purge of NOW, the National Women's Conference in Houston in 1977, and the UN Fourth World Conference on Women in Beijing in 1995. Alexander remains active in the lesbian community on the North Fork of Long Island.
  In this oral history Alexander reflects on her childhood in New Jersey, her education, and her early marriage as a lead-in to her involvement with the women's movement. Alexander details her relationship to Betty Friedan and the National Organization for Women and her painful experiences as part of the lesbian purge. Alexander also describes her life with Mother Courage, the restaurant she opened with partner Jill Ward, which became a hub of radical feminism in the 70s. Lastly, she reflects on her work with Women Against Pornography and the anti-pornography movement's place in feminism. (Transcript 61 pp.)
  Related Materials
  The Dolores Alexander Papers are available for research at Smith College Special Collections.
- Dorothy Allison interviewed by Kelly Anderson, November 18-19, 2007; Allison, Dorothy; Anderson, Kelly (Box 3)
  Dorothy Allison grew up in Greenville, South Carolina, the first child of a fifteen-year-old unwed mother who worked as a waitress. Now living in Northern California with her partner Alix and her teenage son, Wolf Michael, she describes herself as a feminist, a working class story teller, a Southern expatriate, a sometime poet and a happily born-again Californian. Awarded the 2007 Robert Penn Warren Award for Fiction, Allison is a member of the Fellowship of Southern Writers. The first member of her family to graduate from high school, Allison attended Florida Presbyterian College on a National Merit Scholarship and in 1979 studied anthropology at the New School for Social Research. An award winning editor for Quest, Conditions, and Outlook-early feminist and lesbian and gay journals, Allison's chapbook of poetry, The Women Who Hate Me, was published with Long Haul Press in 1983. Her short story collection, Trash(1988) was published by Firebrand Books. Trash won two Lambda Literary Awards and the American Library Association Prize for Lesbian and Gay Writing.
  Allison says that the early feminist movement changed her life. "It was like opening your eyes under water. It hurt, but suddenly everything that had been dark and mysterious became visible and open to change." However, she admits, she would never have begun to publish her stories "if she hadn't gotten over her prejudices, and started talking to her mother and sisters again."
  Allison received mainstream recognition with her novel Bastard Out of Carolina(1992) a finalist for the 1992 National Book Award. The novel won the Ferro Grumley prize, an ALA Award for Lesbian and Gay Writing, became a bestseller, and an award-winning movie. It has been translated into more than a dozen languages. Cavedweller(1998) also became a national bestseller, a NY Times Notable book of the year, a finalist for the Lillian Smith prize, and an ALA prize winner. A novel, She Who, is forthcoming.
  Because Dorothy Allison has written extensively about her childhood and early family life, this oral history focuses on Allison's political activism and involvement with feminism, beginning in Tallahassee, FL in the 1970s. She recounts "finding the movement" at Florida State University through the Women's Center and her parallel life in the bars, among butch-femme dykes, and her struggle to integrate the worlds of middle-class politics and working class erotics. Allison describes her myriad connections to the women's movement-from being a founder of Herstore, a feminist bookstore, to Quest, to the anti-violence movement, to Conditions, and the Lesbian Sex Mafia. Throughout, she offers an uncompromising assessment of feminism's triumphs and failures, particularly through the lenses of class and sexuality. (Transcript 62 pp.)
- Dorothy Allison and Carmen Vásquez interviewed by Kelly Anderson, November 19, 2007; Allison, Dorothy; Vázquez, Carmen M.; Anderson, Kelly (Box 3)
  In this two-hour conversation, Allison and Vázquez tell stories of young adulthood and realizing "who they are," share their journeys through 1970s and 80s feminisms in San Francisco, explore the extensive emphasis on androgyny and hostility towards butch-femme within the lesbian community, and reflect on current debates within the lesbian community over trans identities. (Transcript 48 pp.)
- Virginia Apuzzo Interviewed by Kelly Anderson, June 2-3, 2004; Apuzzo, Virginia; Anderson, Kelly (Box 4)
  Virginia (Ginny) Apuzzo (b.1941) was raised in the Bronx, graduated with a B.A. from SUNY New Paltz and an M.A. from Fordham University, and entered the convent at the age of 26. After leaving the convent, Apuzzo came out publicly as a lesbian, taught at Brooklyn College, and dove head first into movement politics. Working with the then-named National Gay Task Force, Apuzzo worked to have a gay and lesbian plank included in the 1976 Democratic Party platform. Subsequently, she became the Director of the Task Force, directing much of her attention to the AIDS crisis. Apuzzo's impressive political accomplishments led to two decades of political appointments, first with the Cuomo administration and then the Clinton administration, where she was appointed Assistant to the President for Administration and Management, making her the highest ranking out lesbian government official to date. Apuzzo left this post in 1999 when she rejoined the Task Force as the first holder of the Virginia Apuzzo Chair for Leadership in Public Policy. She currently resides in Kingston, New York.
  In this oral history Virginia Apuzzo discusses her family heritage, growing up in an Italian American community in the Bronx, and her choice to enter the convent. The interview is particularly strong in the areas of Catholicism, faith, and spirituality. Apuzzo discusses her coming out process and the ways that her sexuality became her politics. While she touches on the women's movement, the Houston conference, and the impact of feminism in her life, Apuzzo details in depth her relationship to the gay and lesbian movement, in particular her experience with the Task Force. She also describes her campaign for the New York State Assembly and the formation of Lambda Independent Democrats. A significant focus of the interview is Apuzzo's service in the Cuomo and Clinton administrations. (Transcript 96 pp.)
  The Virginia Apuzzo Papers are available for research at Smith College Special Collections.
- Charon Asetoyer Interviewed by Joyce Follet, September 1-2, 2005; Asetoyer, Charon; Follet, Joyce (Box 5)
  Charon Asetoyer was born March 24, 1951, in San Jose, California, the youngest child of Virginia Asetoyer (Comanche) and Charles Eugene Huber. A student organizer as a teen, she dropped out of high school to start her own dress design business in San Francisco. In the late 1960s and early 1970s, she worked at the Urban Indian Health Center and became immersed in the cultural life of Haight-Ashbury and in the American Indian Movement. To escape an abusive marriage, she moved to South Dakota, where she enrolled in the University of South Dakota, earning a degree in criminal justice in 1981. She earned a master's degree in international administration and intercultural management from the School for International Training in Brattleboro, Vermont, in 1983.
  In the mid-1980s, Asetoyer created and briefly directed a health program for Women of All Red Nations (WARN) to address fetal alcohol syndrome on three South Dakota reservations. After marrying Clarence Rockboy, she settled on his Yankton Sioux Reservation in South Dakota, where they set up the Native American Community Board (NACB) in 1985. Their first project was "Women and Children and Alcohol." In 1988 the NACB established the Native American Women's Health Education Resource Center (NAWHERC), which Asetoyer continues to direct.
  NAWHERC gathers information on the health needs of indigenous women in the Aberdeen area (ND, SD, Iowa, Nebraska), provides referral services, runs a domestic violence shelter, and advocates Native rights. The Center maintains programs on domestic violence, AIDS prevention, youth services, adult learning, Dakota language and culture, environmental awareness and action, fetal alcohol syndrome, nutrition, and reproductive health and rights. The Center is noted for its community-based research and publications, which have influenced policies and practices of the Indian Health Service and other agencies.
  NAWHERC works at local and regional levels and also addresses policy issues that affect indigenous women nationally and internationally. Asetoyer has been involved in the Working Group on Indigenous Populations at the United Nations from its early stages and was one of the founding co-chairs of the Working Group's Committee on Health. Asetoyer is an enrolled member of the Comanche Tribe of Oklahoma, and she is active in coalitions with indigenous women and other women of color in the US and internationally. She has served on the boards of the American Indian Center (San Francisco), the National Women's Health Network, the Indigenous Women's Network, the National Environmental Justice Advisory Committee (NEJAC) of the Environmental Protection Agency, and Honor the Earth. During the Clinton Administration she was appointed to one of the National Advisory Councils for Health and Human Services. She has two sons.
  Asetoyer describes her family roots in Oklahoma, her childhood in a biracial family, and her involvement as a teen in the cultural and political life of the Bay Area in the late 1960s and early 1970s. She traces her work with Native women's health programming in South Dakota in the 1980s and her involvement with national and international women of color health activists around such issues as fetal alcohol syndrome and Depo-Provera. Asetoyer explains the workings and programs of the Native American Women's Health Education Resource Center and the centrality of sovereignty to indigenous women's activism. (Transcript 104 pp.)
  The Charon Asetoyer Papers and the Native American Women's Health Education Resource Center Records are available for research at Smith College Special Collections.
- Byllye Avery Interviewed by Loretta J. Ross, July 21-22, 2005; Avery, Byllye; Ross, Loretta J. (Box 6)
  Byllye Yvonne Reddick Avery (b. 1937) was born in Waynesville, Georgia, and grew up in DeLand, Florida. She graduated from Talladega College in 1959 and soon married. Beginning in 1971, Avery became a reproductive freedom advocate working with the Clergy Consultation Service referring women from Florida to New York City for legal abortions before the 1973 Roe v. Wade decision. As one of the few African American reproductive rights activists of her time, she served on the Board of Directors of the National Women's Health Network and worked with the Boston Women's Health Book Collective, authors of Our Bodies, Ourselves. She co-founded an abortion service, the Gainesville Women's Health Center in 1974, and she also co-founded Birthplace, a birthing center, in 1978. In 1983, Avery led the first national conference on Black women's health issues, which launched the National Black Women's Health Project in 1984 in Atlanta, Georgia. In 1989 she was the recipient of a MacArthur "genius" grant in recognition of her pioneering work on Black women's health issues, and that same year received the Essence Award from Essence Magazine. She is now the founder of the Avery Institute for Social Change and the author of An Altar of Words.